If you’re anything like me,
you have lots of ambitious
plans for the future.
I’ve got a whole series of
new books I want to write,
thousands more
videos to script.
But guess what?
None of us may be able to do
any of the things we want to do
if we don't have our health.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Just ate some garlicky hummus?
Great! But you may want to
listen in on our first story.
Approximately
one in three people
suffer from halitosis-
bad breath.
What can we do about it?
I've got videos
on tongue cleaning, gum chewing,
and the best mouthwash.
Population studies suggest
that those who eat
fewer fruits and vegetables
may be at higher risk,
but there are a lot of things
associated with worse diets
that are also linked
to halitosis,
though the fruit
and vegetable link
seemed to remain
even after controlling
for these other factors.
It works in dogs.
Vegetable chew toys
seem to help,
but what about people?
There's a compound found
in cruciferous vegetables
that can effectively eliminate
the volatile sulfur compounds
like the rotten egg gas
hydrogen sulfide.
These are the foul gases
that cause bad breath
produced mainly
from the breakdown
of sulfur-containing
amino acids
concentrated in animal protein-
cysteine and methionine.
The cruciferous compound gloms
onto the sulfur compound
and prevents it
from going gaseous;
whereas peppermint,
spearmint, wintergreen,
and many of the flavors
in breath mints and chewing gum
didn't actually treat the cause,
and just kind of have
a masking effect.
Whereas something
like broccoli chewing gum
might help
at least temporarily,
but why not just eat broccoli
instead?
Researchers have tried
using a compound
that clears cysteine
from the tongue
for those who don't just want
to try to cut down on casein
and other animal proteins
that are concentrated in it.
The compound they used
is derived from kiwi fruit,
so can you just eat kiwis
instead?
No word on halitosis,
but twice daily kiwi fruit
consumption for two months
showed significant improvements
in gingivitis, plaque,
and gum disease.
Of course, not all fruits
are going to be beneficial.
Durian fruit may give rise
to the most profound bad breath
because the fruit itself
stinks to high heaven,
as many of you will remember
from my harrowing experience
with it in medical school
that I sheepishly related
in my book How Not to Die.
And the vegetable
that comes to mind
when you think bad breath
is garlic.
Is there anything you can do
to deodorize garlic breath
using different kinds of foods?
Well, you don't know
until you put it to the test.
After giving people
some garlic,
they tried whey protein,
lemon juice, green tea,
chlorophyll, 7UP soda,
a raw pink lady apple,
a cooked apple, parsley,
spinach, and mint leaves.
Anyone want to take a guess
as to which worked best?
Parsley, spinach,
and mint treatments
were effective
in the deodorization
of garlic breath
stinky compounds.
They're all green,
so they wondered
if it was the chlorophyll,
and it turned out, nope,
chlorophyll alone didn't help.
There are four
stinky garlic compounds.
If you don't do anything
after the garlic,
the stench goes away
on its own.
And taking chlorophyll didn't
seem to change that at all,
but parsley, spinach,
and mint did,
starting almost immediately.
What do we think was going on?
Well, raw apples worked better
than cooked apples,
which are basically
the same food
except for the enzymes
being destroyed by heating,
so maybe there's
some enzymatic deodorization.
Here's the data.
And, yes, raw worked better
than cooked,
but cooked still worked
better than nothing,
and so did the lemon juice
and green tea,
even though they didn't have
any active enzymes
since they were
both pasteurized.
Here's the beverages data.
The whey protein in water
didn't seem to help at all,
even compared with the soda,
though green tea and lemon
appeared to do better.
Maybe the acidic pH
was involved
in the deodorization
from the lemon juice
and soft drink
breath experiments,
since they used
a sour lemon-lime soft drink.
Garlic breath volatiles
(allyl methyl disulfide,
diallyl disulfide,
allyl mercaptan)
were significantly reduced
by parsley, spinach, mint,
raw and microwaved apple,
soft drink, green tea,
and lemon juice treatments
in comparison to water
(the control)
but were not reduced
by chlorophyll
and whey protein treatments.
And perhaps
the polyphenol phytonutrients
were the active ingredient
in green tea.
With consumption
of full-flavor garlic,
it is not yet possible
to completely avoid
malodorous breath associated
with garlic consumption,
but there are some chasers
that may help you
bring it down a notch.
Finally today,
we explore the wondrous properties
of green tea for controlling halitosis.
Tea is the second most widely
consumed beverage in the world,
after water, to the tune of
billions of pounds every year.
In my last video I showed
how drinking green tea
after eating garlic
helps deodorize your breath.
But what about drinking
green tea
to deodorize regular bad breath
without the garlic?
There's been a lot of studies
on the effect of green tea
on other aspects
of oral health.
For example, green tea
appears to work as well
as chlorhexidine
for reducing plaque,
and chlorhexidine
is like the gold standard.
Green tea is safer too.
Chlorhexidine has
so many side effects
you're not supposed to use
if for more than
a short time period;
side effects like discoloration
of the teeth,
increased formation of tartar,
an impairment
of taste sensation,
and occasionally damage
to the inner lining
of your mouth,
whereas if anything,
drinking green tea
appears to have
good side effects.
Tea consumption is associated
with living a longer life
thanks to links
to less cardiac death,
heart disease, stroke,
and type 2 diabetes-
and not just by a little.
A three cup (720 ml)
a day increase
in tea consumption per day
is associated with
a 24 percent decreased risk
of premature death
from all causes put together,
the equivalent of adding
about two years
onto your lifespan.
The longevity link extends
to both green tea and black,
though the per cup effect
appears greater with green.
If you compare
the anti-microbial efficacy
of green tea and chlorhexidine
mouth rinses
against the bacteria
associated with tooth decay
in children with severe
early childhood cavities,
this study found
that a green tea mouth rinse
was superior to chlorhexidine,
but this study
found the opposite.
Chlorhexidine wiped out
like 95 percent
of the decay bacteria,
versus more like 70 percent
for green tea,
but just rinsing
with water alone
can cut levels in half.
So, in terms of
protecting teeth,
the effectiveness of green tea
as a mouth rinse agent
has not been proven.
But what about for bad breath?
The effect of green tea
on halitosis
has evidently been well known
from early times,
perhaps due
to the deodorizing activity
of certain
antioxidant polyphenols.
But you don't really know
until you put it to the test.
This study found that sucking
on green tea tablets
reduced stinky breath compounds,
but who sucks on tea tablets?
Here, green tea was compared
to breath mints, chewing gum,
and parsley oil,
and green tea seemed to help,
but did not reach
statistical significance.
But again, it wasn't drinking
or swishing with green tea,
but rather
some green tea powder
sprinkled on people's tongues.
This study used actual tea
and found
that one minute later,
swishing with green tea
was no better
than swishing with water.
Okay, but what about chronic use
over time?
This is the study
I had been looking for.
A randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
in which people
rinsed their mouths twice a day
for a month
with a green tea mouthwash
or a similar looking/tasting
placebo mouthwash.
And at the end of the month,
the stinky bad breath compounds
were reduced nearly 40 percent
in the green tea group versus
closer to only 10 percent
in the placebo group.
Bottom line:
a systematic review
on the effect of the tea plant
on decreasing
the level of halitosis
concluded
that green tea mouthwash
can indeed reduce bad breath,
though they don't feel
the evidence
is sufficiently robust
for dentists
to start recommending it
on its own
due to lack of enough
randomized clinical studies.
But green tea mouthwash can be
a good treatment of choice
beside other halitosis
treatments,
like tongue scraping,
to achieve
better clinical results.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you want to see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age” has
been out for about half a year now.
Check it out from your
local public library.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.